What effect, if any, does a
vegetarian or plant-based diet
have on athletic performance?
Watch the video to find out.
"The Gladiator Diet and the
First Studies on Vegetarian Athletes"
Recently, the remains of
dozens of Roman gladiators
were discovered in a mass grave.
The clue to their identities
were the rather distinct types
of mortal injuries they found,
like being speared in
the head with a trident.
Using just their skeletons
they were able to reconstruct
the death blows, show just
how buff they really were,
and even try to reconstruct
their diet of barley and beans.
You can look at carbon isotopes and
see what kinds of plants they ate;
nitrogen isotopes reflect any
intake of animal protein.
You can also look at the
Sulphur in their bones
and the amount of strontium,
leading commentators to submit
that the best athletes
in ancient Rome ate
largely plant-based diets.
Then there were the legionnaires,
the Roman army troopers,
famed for their abilities, also
eating a similar kind of diet,
suggesting “the best fighters
in the ancient world
were essentially vegetarian.”
So, if the so-called
perfect fighting machines,
the great sports heroes of the day,
were eating mostly grains and beans,
should that tell us anything
about sports nutrition
and the preferred diets
of elite athletes?
Well, most of the Greeks and
Romans were basically vegetarian,
centering their diets around
grains, fruit, vegetables and beans,
so maybe the gladiators’ diets
weren’t that remarkable.
Plato, for example, pushed
plants, preferring plant foods
for their health and efficiency.
So yes, the Roman gladiators
were known as the ‘‘barley men,’’
but is that because barley
gives you strength and stamina,
or was that just the basic food
that people ate at the time,
not necessarily for performance,
but because it was just so cheap?
Well, if you look at the modern
Spartans, the Tarahumara Indians,
the ones that run races where
they kick a ball for oh,
75 miles just for the fun of it,
running all day, all night,
and all day, maybe 150 miles
if they’re feeling in the mood.
What do you get if you win?
A special popularity with the ladies
(although how much of a reward
that would actually prove to be
for a man who had been running
for two days straight is questionable;
though, maybe their endurance
extends to other dimensions).
“Probably not since the
days of the ancient Spartans
has a people achieved such a high
state of extreme physical conditioning.”
And what did they eat?
The same kind of 75 to
80 percent starch diet
based on beans, corn, and squash.
And, they had the cholesterol
levels to prove it,
total cholesterol levels down at an
essentially heart attack proof 136.
And it’s not just some
special genetics they have—
you feed them enough egg yolks and
their cholesterol creeps right up.
Modern day Olympian runners
eat the same stuff.
What are they eating over there in Kenya?
A 99 percent vegetarian diet centered
mostly around various starches.
But as in all these cases, is
their remarkable physical prowess
because of their diets, or
in spite of their diets?
Or have nothing to do with their diets?
You don’t know…until
you put it to the test.
In spite of well-documented health
benefits of more plant-based diets,
less is known regarding the effects
of these diets on athletic performance.
So, they compared elite vegetarian
and omnivore endurance athletes
for aerobic fitness and strength.
So, comparing oxygen
utilization on the treadmill,
and quad strength with leg extensions.
And the vegetarians beat out
their omnivore counterparts
for cardiorespiratory fitness,
but their strength didn’t differ.
Suggesting, in the very least,
that vegetarian diets
don’t compromise athletic performance.
But this was a cross-sectional study.
Maybe the veg athletes were just
fitter because they trained harder?
Like in the National Runners' Health Study
looking at thousands of runners:
vegetarian runners were recorded
running significantly
more on a weekly basis;
so, maybe that explains
their superior fitness.
Though, maybe their superior fitness
explains their greater distances.
Other cross-sectional studies
have found no differences
in physical fitness between
vegetarian and non-vegetarian athletes,
or even worse performance, as in this
study of vegetarian athletes in India.
Of course, there could be socioeconomic
or other confounding factors.
That’s why we need interventional
studies to put different diets
to the test and then compare
physical performance,
which we’ll explore next.
In 1896, the aptly named
James Parsley evidently led
a successful vegetarian
cycling club to victory,
their competitors evidently having
to "eat crow with their beef."
Evidently some Belgian
put it to the test in 1904,
with those eating more plant-based
supposedly lifting some weight
like 80 percent more times,
but I couldn't find the
primary source in English.
This I could find though: a famous
series of experiments at Yale,
published more than a century ago, on the
influence of flesh-eating on endurance.
Forty-nine people were compared:
regular athletes (mostly Yale students),
vegetarian athletes, and then
just sedentary vegetarians.
"The experiment furnished a severe test
of the claims of those flesh-abstainers."
Much to the researchers' surprise,
the results seemed to vindicate
the vegetarians, suggesting that
not eating meat leads to far greater
endurance compared to those accustomed
to the ordinary American diet.
Check it out: the first endurance test was
how many minutes straight you could
hold out your arms horizontally:
flesh-eaters versus flesh abstainers.
The regular Yale athletes were
able to keep their hands out
for about 10 minutes on average.
It's harder than it sounds;
give it a try...
OK, but those eating vegetarian
did like five times better.
The meat-eater maximum was only
half that of the vegetarian average.
Only two meat eaters
even hit 15 minutes,
whereas more than two-thirds
of the meat-avoiders did.
None of the regular diet
folks hit a half hour,
whereas nearly half of
the healthier eaters did,
including nine that exceeded an
hour, four that exceeded two hours,
and one guy going for
more than three hours.
How many deep knee
bends can you do?
One athlete could do more
than 1,000—averaging 383—
but they got creamed even
by the sedentary plant-eaters.
That's the crazy thing; even
the sedentary abstainers
surpassed the exercising flesh-eaters.
The sedentary abstainers were,
in most cases, physicians
who sat on their butts all day.
I want a doctor that that can do
a thousand deep knee bends!
And then in terms of recovery, all those
deep knee bends left everyone sore,
but more so among those eating meat.
Among the vegetarians, of two that
did like 2,000 knee bends, one went
straight off to the track to run and
another went on to their nursing duties.
On the other hand, among the
meat-eaters one guy reached 254,
went down once more and couldn't
get back up, had to be carried away,
and was incapacitated for days; another
impaired for weeks after fainting.
It may be inferred without reasonable
doubt, concluded the once skeptical
Yale researcher, that the meat-eating
group of athletes was very far inferior
in endurance to the vegetarians,
even the sedentary ones.
What could account for
this remarkable difference?
Some claimed that flesh foods contained
some kind of "fatigue poisons,"
but one German researcher who detailed
his own experiments with athletes
offered a more prosaic answer.
In his book on what looks like
physiological studies of
uber-driving vegetarians—
I told you I only know English—
he conjectured that the apparent
vegetarian superiority was just due
to their tremendous determination
to prove their point
and spread their propaganda,
so they just make a greater effort
in any contest than do
their meat-eating rivals.
The Yale researchers were worried
about this, and so special pains
were taken to stimulate the flesh-eaters
to the utmost, appealing to
their college pride. Don't let those lousy
vegetarians beat the "Yale spirit."
The experiments made it
into The New York Times.
Yale's flesh-eating athletes—
sounds like a zombie movie—
beaten in severe endurance tests.
Yale professor believes that
he has shown definitely the inferiority
in strength and endurance tests
of meat eaters compared to
those who do not eat meat.
Some of Yale's most successful
athletes took part in the strength tests,
and Professor Fisher declares they
were obliged to admit their inferiority.
How has the truth of this result
been so long obscured?
One reason, Professor Fisher
suggested, is that vegetarians
are their own worst enemy.
In their fanaticism, they jump
from the premise that meat eating
is wrong—often based on scripture
or some kind of dogma—and jump
from that to meat-eating is unhealthy.
That's not how science works
and such logical leaps get them
dismissed as zealots and prevent
any genuine scientific investigation.
Lots of science, even back then,
was pointing a distinct trend
towards more plant-based eating,
and yet the word vegetarian—
even 110 years ago—had
such a bad, preachy rap
that many were loath to concede
the science in its favor.
The proper scientific attitude is to study
the question of meat-eating in precisely
the same manner as one would
study the question of anything else.